Guide to the Imre Forbáth diaries,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Imre Forbáth Diaries, 1900-1943
  - Journal 19:: December 21, 1937 - November 11, 1939 (Box 4)
    In 1938, the First Jewish law comes into effect, restricting the number of Jews in the professions and in commercial enterprises to twenty percent. The Jews are being shut out of Hungarian society. Imrédi is forced to resign when it is found that one of his great-grandparents was Jewish. The new Prime Minister, Pál Teleki, pushes through the Second Jewish Law, even harsher and more restrictive than the First. He announces the return of Kárpátalja (Subcarpathia) to Hungary. Military conscription is re-introduced. Young Jews are leaving the country by the thousands. Imre Forbáth discusses these events with his son, Tamás, and wants to send him abroad. After finishing high school on July 12, 1939, Tamás leaves for the Royal College in London, where he prepares for the science examination in the summer. Many young British men have applied to the same college this year, because of conscription; a Royal College degree will automatically make them officers. Feeling he will have a better chance elsewhere, he transfers to the faculty of technology of the University of Manchester.
    Forbath won a Third Place for the Plans for the Exhibition and Market Area in Vienna
    Agotay
    Archer, Pal
    Aschner, Pal
    Aurel, Egry
    Babianu
    Balint, Emma
    Balint, Jozsef
    Barabas, Andon
    Bcher, Lenke
    Bece
    Bereczelli
    Bruck, Tamás
    Cariaes (Professor)
    Desseffy, Miklosne
    Dipscher, Istvánne
    Domony
    Drajomiseanu
    Drinda
    Fekete, Sandorne (Dr.)
    Ferko Boni
    Fleischmann (Dr.)
    Forbáth, Sandor (Dr.)
    Frazer (Miss)
    Fuhrer, Miklos
    German (Dr.)
    Gerna
    Gluckothal
    Grumer
    Gyeresi, Gabor
    Halom
    Hatvany, Lajos
    Hollosy, Odon
    Horvth, Lipot
    Icheiser
    Kapri (Baron)
    Lobeger
    Magyarkallay Miksa
    Marffy
    Mikus, Manci
    Murgusiau
    Nagy, Zsiga
    Noldy
    Okanyi, András
    Pajor (Dr.)
    Picler, Henrik
    Polya, Tibor
    Pompery, Elemer
    Popper, Edit
    Rapoch
    Rocheri, Charlie
    Rogi, Frank
    Rudko
    Saluiszky
    Spiero
    Stein, Emil
    Szechenyi, Balint
    Tamás, Arpad
    Ungvar, Imre
    Vikar, Geza
    Viovai, Robert
    Vlentin
    Belgradi Városkozpont (Belgrade’s Downtown), Ter és Forma
    Bibliography of Imre Forbáth by Dr. Palfy-Endre Budinszky
    Epulo Buda (Building Buda), Budai Naplo
    Imre Forbáth’s biography and his picture, Köpfe (The Head) publishes, Neue Freie Presse
    Interview with Imre Forbáth in Budai Naplo
    Margit koruti epitkezesekrol (On the Building of the Margit Beltway), Budai Naplo
    Megjegyzesek a várbeli Julian Szobor felirataihoz (Comments on the Inscriptions on the Julian Statue at the Castle), Budai Naplo
    Pozsony Kispesti Foter, Bratislava, Kispest’s Main Square, Ter és Forma
    Uj epitesi szabalyok (New Rules on Building), Budai Naplo
    Városepites Torokországban (City Building in Turkey), Vallalkozok Lapja
    Wien Ausstellungspläne (Plans for the Exhibition Area in Vienna), Ter és Forma
    Zur Frage ders Taban Hotels (On the Question of the Hotels in Taban), Ter és Forma
    Building Buda
    New Rules on Building
    Vilagkiallitasok Parizsban (World Fairs in Paris), Lipotvárosi Kamara
    Expert on the Water Supply for the Paper Factory in Szentendre
    Expert on the Water Supply of the Csepel Cellulose Factory
    First Drafts of the Danube Waterworks in Obuda
    Goldberg Factory’s Water Supply
    Watering and Canalization of Újvidék
  - Journal 20: November 12, 1939 - December 20, 1941 (Box 4)
    In 1939, Imre Forbáth obtains his parents’ and grandparents’ papers, which prove that the family has lived in Nyitra, Hungary since 1815. The entire Hungarian population is being compelled to produce similar proofs.
    The Budapest office of the Nitrogen Factory is liquidated. Due to the war, the Cartel is abolished. The factory in Diciosanmartin continues its liquidation process. Forbáth and Dr. Vajda give the records of the Nitrogen Factory to Bucharest. There is an accidental explosion in the Chlorine Factory in Zernest, resulting in a large number of casualties.
    At the end of September 1939, Washington announces the Sixteenth International Builders’ Conference. Forbáth sends a contribution on the theme “The Relationship between Population Density and Buildings.” He is invited to the conference but is unable to attend due to the war.
    Ag, Peti
    Bauer
    Bence, Gyla
    Berczelli
    Borbas, Lajos
    Deli
    Dreitner, Erich
    Emigrants
    Ferencz, Pali
    Gelieren, Mark, van
    Gombos, Laszlo
    Harry
    Heves, Bandi and Pityu
    Horvath, Lipoth (and family)
    Krefonerni (and daughter)
    Mezei, Veronika
    Molnar, Imre (Dr.)
    Oppler, Pista (family)
    Opples, Emil
    Papp, Lilly (and her husband)
    Pogany, Bela (family)
    Polya, Jancsi (family)
    Popock
    Riemes, Jozsi
    Schwarz, Alfred (family)
    Szentgyorgyi (Professor)
    Torok
    Ullmann
    Vadasz
    Viray, Imre
    Walkiden
    Wolf, Nazi (Farkas, Naci)
    Wottitz
    Waterworks Plan of the Danube for the Goldberger Factory at Obuda
  - Journal 21: December 21, 1941 - December 25, 1943 (Box 4)
    The Office of Land Registry takes away Forbáth’s orchard in Bugyi; however, the family rents it back from the government. Imre Forbáth’s membership in the Board of Engineers ends. He loses his voting rights. He must fill out a survey about how his home can be shared, and about his Jewish origins. It has been 25 years since he returned from Siberian captivity. Dr. Arthur Kovacs, a fellow former prisoner of war, holds a gathering to remember their time in the Nikolok Ussurisk prison camp.
    At the suggestion of one of his professors, Tamás Forbáth leaves England and travels to America because of the war. In 1942, he earns a B. S. in Chemical Engineering at Columbia University in New York. He is able to communicate with his family only very rarely. In Hungary, the male members of the Forbáth family are drafted for labor service. Tamás’s former high school classmates write to Imre Forbáth for support. They have been in labor service in Transylvania for two years. They work barefoot, without blankets, coats, or food. One of them was the national high school champion in mathematics. Forbáth sends them financial aid. The Pro-Palestine Association also asks Forbáth for donations. Imre Forbáth does not have work during the war. He takes care of his properties and he serves as an air raid warden in his community. He tries to build new shelters. Forbáth is thinking about death. He reads texts from the Old and New Testaments. He looks for reasons for the tragic fate of the Jews. He has faith that the worst will never happen in Hungary. He believes that the following year will be a year of wise decisions.
    Andor
    Barta
    Bencsik
    Dan
    Denes, Klara
    Farkas, Heidi
    Forro (Dr.)
    Fried, Pal
    Fritz, Jeno
    Gessler
    Glesinger, Emil
    Guszti, Alcsuty
    Heisler
    Herceg, Klara
    Herman, Lipot
    Katona
    Kemeny
    Klenovics
    Koranyi
    Kosa
    Krauzner
    Kunváry, Bella
    Laczko, Andor
    Lord
    Ludekes, Tiborne
    Magyar
    Mandl, Imre
    Markos, Viktor
    Muller, Dora
    Nagy, Bela
    Okanyi
    Palocz, Bodog
    Patek
    Pekri, Geza
    Polya, Jeno
    Popper, Laci
    Proszvimer
    Puzios
    Rapech, Geza
    Rapeck, Andor
    Roszvinner
    Sarkany, Feri
    Stein, Sandor
    Szabo, Guszti
    Szentirmay (Dr.)
    Talgay-Roth, Miklos
    Ullmann, Andor
    Virag (Professor)
    Weber, Tibor
    Wetzl
    ador
    A Budai Kilato ut (Road to the Look Out Tower at Buda), Budai Kronika (in the Emlekkonyv, which was left out due to paper shortages)
    Milliok evacualasara kepes város terve (About a City Capable of Evacuating Millions), Magyar Nemzet
    Városepites a haboru utan (City Building after the War)
  - Inserts found in diaries
    - Letter to Tamas, 11 November, 1941, Budapest (fragment, typescript) (Box 4)
    - Photographs
      - Forbath, Imre, 1932 (Box 4)
      - Forbath, Imre with family, 1929 (Box 4)
    - Business card (with a holograph note) (Box 4)
    - Book-Plate (with a holograph note on a back) (Box 4)